Good morning everybody.
Welcome. Today's דף daf on the 18th of תמוז Tamuz is the
sixth דף daf of פסחים. Pesachim. We are going to pick up
on the two dots of ה' עמוד ב', Hei Amud Bet, right
where the lines get wide.
And I really hope to really plow through the דף daf today
and get more towards the end and talk a little bit about
the nature of ביטול חמץ bittul chametz because there's definitely some good
stuff to say and I'm hoping that I'll get the opportunity to
share that with you. Okay, so yesterday we were talking about
the
scope of
the איסור issur of בל יראה בל ימצא Bal Yera'eh Bal Yimatze
that it will apply to your חמץ chametz whether or not it
is in your house,
because there's one פסוק pasuk that talks about בבתיכם, bevateichem, there's another
one talks about בגבולך, bigvulecha, so that extends the איסור issur and
it's not and if you look, you need both פסוקים pesukim to
basically tell you that what applies to one applies to the other.
Because if you just had one פסוק pasuk you might say alright,
you're allowed to maybe bury it. No, it can't be found. And
okay, maybe it can't be found in your house, but it can
be found in your field, your caves, whatever, cisterns, that type of
stuff. No, you can't do that either.
However though, the גמרא Gemara points out that there was
a seeming contradiction, this is where we're going to start for today,
אמר מר: Amar Mar: יכול יטמן ויקבל פקדונות מן הנכרים? Yachol yitman
ve-yekabel pikdonot min ha-nochrim?
So in that whole lengthy statement
we
dealt with at the end of yesterday, which I was just summarizing,
the position was advanced that perhaps you might have thought that
you could hide your חמץ chametz or you can accept פקדון pikadon
from some, you know, from a נכרי nochri because, you know, that
may be okay because then that חמץ chametz is not yours. No,
nevertheless
תלמוד לומר: Talmud Lomar: לא ימצא. Lo yimatze. You can't do it
because the
פסוק pasuk
says לא ימצא. Lo yimatze.
Okay, but הא אמרת רישא שלך אי אתה רואה אבל אתה רואה
של אחרים של גבוה? ha amarta reisha shelcha iy atah ro'eh aval
atah ro'eh shel acherim shel gavo'ah? But didn't we say לא יראה
לך? Lo Yera'eh Lecha? So we said from that, oh, you can't
see yours, but you can see others, and you can see, you
know, quote unquote הקדש חמץ. hekdesh chametz So what's going on? We
just said a second ago לא ימצא Lo yimatze excludes you from
getting פקדונות pikdonot from the נכרים, nochrim, but why should that be
a problem? It's not your חמץ. chametz.
In other words, the נכרי nochri is asking you to watch his
Oreo cookies.
Correct.
So either that's a problem or it's not a problem.
No, in the case of the Oreo cookies, correct.
One more day then everyone goes back. So which is it, right?
That's the question. It is or isn't a problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well, it depends. And we're going to be talking about
that more today. הא דקביל עליה אחריות הא דלא קביל עליה אחריות.
Ha de-kibbel alei achrayut ha de-lo kibbel alei achrayut. So it depends
if you're accepting responsibility for it. Like, you know, like we have
שומר חינם, shomer chinam, שומר שכר, shomer sachar, that kind of stuff,
but
basically
then what it turns out that if you're accepting responsibility, so like
let's say something happens to his חמץ, chametz. you're going to have
to make good on it, then this is as if it's yours.
Then you're not allowed to accept it. If you didn't accept responsibility
for his חמץ, chametz, then it's not yours, it's somebody else's, and
that's the חמץ chametz, you're allowed to have seen because it's not
yours.
Okay.
Okay, and just this is a parallel to a case, הא דאמר
להו רבא לבני מחוזא, ha de-amar lehu Rava li-venei Mechuza, just like
רבא Rava said to the people who lived in מחוזא, Mechuza, which
is that city,
he says: בערו חמירא דבני חילא מבתיכון. Ba'iru chamira di-venei cheila mibateichun.
So
you know, one of these things
that in colonial America that they objected to was having to house
the British soldiers. So, same idea, this isn't anything new. Just like
רבא Rava said to the people of מחוזא: Mechuza: בערו חמירא דבני
חילא מבתיכון כיון דאילו מגנב ואילו מיתביד ברשותיכון קאי ובעיתו לשלומי כדילכון
דמי ואסור.
Ba'iru chamira di-venei cheila mibateichun keivan di-illu migna ve-illu mitabed birshuteichun kai
ve-bayitu
lishalumei kedileichon dami ve-assur.
So basically what that's all saying is, well, you have to quarter
their soldiers, so too, just like if they have
their provisions, so you didn't necessarily need to fully feed them, but
they bring their חמץ chametz with them and if that חמץ chametz
of theirs would become lost or stolen, that's מגנב migna or מיתביד,
mitabed, it would become stolen or lost, then ברשותיכון, birshuteichun, it's in
your domain, and it would be yours and it's forbidden. It's like
your possession, you'd need to repay it ואיתי לשלומי, ve'itey lishlumei, you'd
have to pay it back, therefore it is כדלכון kedilchon like yours
and אסור דמי ואסור. assur d'mei ve'assur. So that's basically what we
were saying before just like a second ago. Just like if you're
accepting responsibility for the פקדון pikadon of a נכרי, nochri, it becomes
like yours and then it's אסור, assur, so too these people in
מחוזא Mechuza when they were housing, I guess, housing these soldiers, they
had to get rid of the חמץ chametz that they left there.
Because that could bring about how'd you say that?
Yes. I was going to say I don't know how that practically
worked. I mean,
with the soldiers going to be taking revenge on you for burning
their possessions,
right? That can lead to some serious issues here, right? So but
nevertheless from a halachic perspective, the point being made is that if
you're responsible for it, it's like yours and it would be a
problem to have it over פסח. Pesach. Okay,
so now we're going to question this premise.
One interesting thing there is that you're not taking responsibility for their
חמץ.
chametz
You are held responsible.
That's different.
Yeah, that's why it's a I don't want to belabor it but
it's an interesting case because, yeah.
So now הניחא למאן דאמר
דבר הגורם לממון כממון
דמי, haniicha leman de'amar davar hagorem lemamon kemamon dami,
which is a separate מחלוקת machlokes and we're going to basically say
that at some
point it's going to be losing its parallel. But basically, this is
the issue of sort of גרמא, grama, if you will. So what
we're basically saying is that well listen, so since the loss of
a חמץ chametz. of this other person's חמץ chametz would cost this
person
in whose house it is,
he'd have to pay back the נכרי, nochri, so that means it's
considered yours, right? It's דבר הגורם לממון, davar hagorem lemamon, right? It's
not actually yours but since it's going to cause you to pay
money, so it's as if it's yours, כממון דמי. kemamon dami. Yes,
that's what we're saying. So that's okay if you hold that principle,
but let's say you don't? אלא למאן דאמר לאו כממון דמי מאי
איכא למימר? ella leman de'amar lav kemamon dami mai ika lemeimar? So
why would you be חייב chayav for having this person's חמץ?
chametz That's exactly right.
שאני הכא דאמר לא ימצא, shani hacha de'amar lo yimatzei, it's different
because the תורה Torah says לא ימצא, lo yimatzei, so it's an
extra חומרא chumra basically is what we're saying. So it can't be
found even if, generally in regular
cases דבר הגורם לממון לאו כממון דמי, davar hagorem lemamon lav kemamon
dami, in this case the תורה Torah says it is. So it's
an exception.
איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, so others actually have it a little bit
differently. הניחא למאן דאמר דבר הגורם לממון לאו כממון דמי. haniicha leman
de'amar davar hagorem lemamon lav kemamon dami. No, it actually this makes
more sense if you're saying that generally דבר הגורם לממון davar hagorem
lemamon is not כממון דמי, kemamon dami, היינו דאיצטריך לא ימצא. hainu
de'itztrich lo yimatzei. That's why we have this special פסוק pasuk of
לא ימצא lo yimatzei to tell you even though in most cases
this wouldn't be an issue, in this case it is. אלא למאן
דאמר כממון דמי, ella leman de'amar kemamon dami, but the one who
says that generally it is considered like ממון, mamon, why need the
special פסוק? pasuk? I would have known anyway, right? אלא למאן דאמר
כממון דמי לא ימצא למה לי?
ella leman de'amar kemamon dami
lo yimatzei lama li?
I
don't
need that פסוק. pasuk. In general I hold that it is as
if it's yours. It would be a סברא. svara.
Exactly. So if you have that סברא, svara, you don't need the
פסוק. pasuk.
Exactly, precisely.
Is it always the case, in other words every case in which
you could have a סברא, svara, it's questionable about the דרשה drasha
of the פסוק? pasuk? You know it's interesting, it's not consistent.
Often times they say that, and sometimes you have a פסוק pasuk
repeated and they say לבא עליו בשני לאוין, lavo alav bishnei lavin,
right? But sometimes oh yeah, I don't really need that פסוק, pasuk,
and sometimes they say oh if it's not for this ענין, inyan,
it's for another ענין. inyan. Yeah, but other times they say no,
it is for this ענין inyan and you're עובר over twice. But
generally they really try to use every פסוק pasuk for a reason.
Yeah, I understand that because סברות svaros are as powerful as פסוקים.
psukim. Apparently, yeah. Very interesting.
Okay, yeah, that's a good point. So what do we need this
פסוק? pasuk? אלא איצטריך, ella itztrich, I do need it. סלקא דעתך
אמינא הואיל וכי איתיה הדר בעיניה לאו ברשותיה קאי קמשמע לן.
salka da'atcha amina ho'il vechi ityei hadar be'einei
lav birshutei kai kamashma lan. So basically
in the case, without getting to the whole case of where this
דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי davar hagorem lemamon kemamon dami actually is,
but that was a case where like let's say it was stolen
from you, you don't have it anymore, then are you liable or
not? Like let's say קדשים kodshim וחייב באחריותן, ve'chayav be'achrayutan, then you
don't have it anymore. It was lost, got stolen or something like
that. So you don't have it anymore. But this is a case
where you're going to have it the whole time potentially. In other
words, you'd be giving back his חמץ chametz? to him, right? Like
let's say you didn't have to get rid of it. And this
non-Jewish soldier is in your house, it's פסח, Pesach, you didn't need
his חמץ chametz now, then his regiment
packs
up and leaves, so you'd give him his חמץ chametz back. So
you may have thought listen, it was given to me, I don't
really want it, it's really not mine, it's his, when he leaves
I'm going to give it back to him, so you may have
said in that kind of a case
it's
not mine and I wouldn't be עובר על בל יראה ובל ימצא.
over al bal yira'eh ubal yimatzei. So no, comes the פסוק, Pasuk,
comes the פסוק Pasuk to tell you, even then you are.
Okay, that's pretty, pretty Draconian.
Yeah. Yeah.
Now we're onto a separate case. Now since we were dealing with,
if you will, like the ownership of a נכרי Nochri on חמץ,
chametz now we're going to take a
case
where not חמץ, Chametz, but where there's an ownership of a נכרי.
Nochri. And now remember,
there
are certain things you need to do, you need to give בכור,
Bechor, you need to give מעשר, Ma'aser, right? We learned back in
קדשים Kodashim or were going to learn in קדשים Kodashim later, whichever
way you want to look at it, that
if
there's a part ownership between you and a non-Jew in this בהמה
Behemah that would be a בכור, Bechor, right, are you חייב chayav
or are you not? So basically, it has to be yours and
entirely yours in order to be חייב בבכורה. chayav bivchorah.
Michael, just before you go on, yes, the thing you did just
a minute ago, והשתא דאהדר בעיני. v'hashta d'ahadar b'einei.
Right,
in other words, בעיני.
b'einei. It's not the חמץ Chametz, that's בעיני, b'einei, it's the guy
himself, it's the owner.
No, it's the חמץ Chametz that is. It is. Yeah. In other
words, when he leaves, like, you know, you're going to give his
חמץ Chametz back to him.
Correct. Right. The case where the
original principle
of
דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי davar hagorem l'mamon k'mamon dami would be
a case where
it was an animal, but literally it means when he goes, he
will return the actual substance of the חמץ Chametz
back to him.
Right. So there was never a presupposition that it was in any
way really his.
That's basically what we're saying you would have thought that, right? In
other words, he's in my house, it's his חמץ, Chametz when he
leaves I'm giving it back to him. So why would it be
mine?
But he's in the house the whole time.
Even if he's not, when he, you know, like goes back and
forth and then he packs up, I'm still giving it back to
him, right? So it's בעיני b'einei and it's not mine, right?
I still, it's still his.
So therefore I would have thought that it's never my
question about, it would have never come to your mind to think
it was in any way yours at any moment of that time.
Correct, right. And that's what the פסוק Pasuk to tell you otherwise.
Okay. So back to the בכור. Bechor.
So if the non-Jew has a part ownership in this בכור, Bechor,
then I'm no longer obligated to give this בהמה Behemah as a
בכור. Bechor. Now, but let's say he doesn't really have an ownership
in this specific animal. Like let's say taxes, right?
Just like, well, you know, we need to give מעשר Ma'aser to,
you know, a tenth. Well, guess what, the government, you know, has
its tenth also. But it doesn't have a tenth in this specific
animal, you just have to give it a tenth, right? So let's
say they're telling you, alright, listen,
we're going to take a tenth of your cattle. So does that,
like, is that considered like a תפיסה, tefisah, right? Does the fact
that the non-Jewish government is, is it considered like having a lien
on this בכור Bechor basically? That's the question. בעי רבא בהמת ארנונא,
Ba'ei Rava behemot arnona, that's this case ארנונא, arnona, חייבת בבכורה או
אין חייבת בבכורה? chayevet bivchorah o ein chayevet bivchorah?
Yes or no? כל היכא דמצי מסלק ליה בזוזי לא קמיבעיא לן
דחייב.
Kol heicha d'matzi mesalek lei
b'zuzi lo kamiba'aya lan d'chayav.
As long as you can pay off, you know, the government, as
long as it's a case where the government doesn't really care how
you give them their money, right? In other words, what they really
want, they don't really want particularly your sheep over there, they just
want tax revenue, right? So they don't mind and maybe even potentially
prefer if you just give them the actual money. If you don't
have the money, then, you know, they'll take the value of it
by taking this animal. So if it's a case where you can
literally pay them off, then certainly you would be חייב chayav as
in
בכורה. bechorah. Because then it's certainly not viewed as if he owns
a share of the animal. So when is our question, when does
this even come into play? כי קמיבעיא לן היכא דלא מצי מסלק
ליה בזוזי מאי.
Ki kamiba'aya lan heicha d'lo matzi mesalek lei
b'zuzi mai. So you can't pay them off. They actually really want,
they really want, you know, a tenth of your herd. But does
that mean that this, that it goes onto every animal now in
your herd? Or is it some sort of like general thing? So
is there general lien, if you will, enough to be considered an
owner in this בכור Bechor to exempt you?
Obviously, the government doesn't want the specific one that you designated as
a בכור. Bechor. Right, in other words, you're saying the government has
an interest in a tenth of your animals in the...
Right, in other words, does that mean, right, basically. I mean, or
is it, you know, so is it viewed as being that they
have a tenth of this
animal or is it viewed as more abstract? They just have a
tenth, but it's not be this animal, I can give them another
animal that's not a בכור, Bechor, right? So I give them the
second one and then if that's the case then I would be
חייב
בבכור.
chayav b'bechor.
מאי? Mai? So they asked him, אמר להו פטורה. Amar lehu peturah.
He
said to
them, פטורה. peturah. So which is it? Is it פטור patur or
is it חייב? chayav? No, התם דמצי מסלק ליה. hatam de'matzi messalek
lei. No, that's a different case. That wasn't the case. That's where
you can pay them off. So basically what we said right now
is if you can pay them off, then you're certainly חייב בבכור.
chayav be'bechor. If you can't pay them off, then you can't. That's
where we're up to right now. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, but there's
a different version of this. אמר רב פפא במתניתא ואמרינן פטורא מן
הבכורה. Amar Rav Papa b'matnita ve'amrinan patura min ha'bechora.
So as opposed to what we just said a second ago that
you're חייב, chayav, we now he's saying פטור, patur, but אף
על גב דמצי
מסלק ליה,
af al gav de'matzi
messalek lei, even though you can pay him off, nevertheless it's פטור
מן הבכורה. patur min ha'bechora. But however we have another principle that
מראשית עריסותיכם me'reishit arisoteichem for חלה, Challah, right? When you make your
kneading, when you knead your חלה Challah and it's reaching at a
certain
point, kneading your dough, it has to be מראשית עריסותיכם me'reishit arisoteichem
to be חייב בחלה. chayav be'Challah. So but let's say the, you
know, same case but now they have an interest in your,
whatever, your food, I mean your bread stuff.
They'd be חייב בחלה. chayav be'Challah. In that case, עיסת הארנונא חייבת
בחלה. isat ha'arnona chayavet be'Challah. ואף על גב דלא מצי מסלק ליה.
ve'af al gav de'lo matzi messalek lei.
It's still חייב chayav and even if they specifically would want your
חלה Challah and you can't pay them off. So what's the difference?
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why are we saying בהמה behemah is פטור
patur but עיסה isah is חייב? chayav? בהמה אית ליה קלא עיסה
לית ליה קלא.
Behemah it lei kala, isah
leit lei kala. So what he's really saying is really it should
be, you really should be exempt in both cases.
But
what we're going to say is that the בהמה behemah you'd be
basically you're פטור, patur, right? Because, you know, everyone knows, like, you
know, okay, yeah, you know, like cattle's more
important. So people are talking about cattle, so people would and presumably,
you know, these kind of things are also more publicized. Oh, you
know, the collector's coming and you know he's going to take from
your cattle. So everyone kind of knows
that he has this lien, and so that should be transferring to
חלה Challah as well. But people aren't really talking about necessarily like,
you know, the bread and, you know, is the government coming to
take like one of my chocolate chip cookies over there, right?
So people are going to somehow not, they're not going to know
that the government has an interest in it, but yet they are,
but are going to be looking to see whether you took חלה
Challah or not. So it's like one of these kind of things
and so then they see you're not taking חלה. Challah. So they're
going to think, what? This guy isn't taking, isn't taking חלה? Challah?
How can that be? So they're going to, you know, it may
be like a מראית עין marit ayin issue. So
that's the way, the government or non-Jewish? The non-Jewish government.
And they care about חלה? Challah?
No, no, no. The point is is their ownership,
is their ownership, right?
And they're going to take it from your food, you know, the
value of your food. Let's say you're a baker, they'll take whatever.
So somehow that's not going to be as well known, but then
people are going to see then somehow that's not going to be
known that they have an interest in it, but what is going
to be known to everyone else is that you know you're not
taking חלה Challah from it. And that's not going to look too
good.
So
they're going to say why isn't this guy taking חלה? Challah? I
know, but
that's what I'm saying, I don't know how they know. I know,
but that's
what I'm saying. How are they going to know
that and everybody's, I mean everybody knows the government
policy. I know, I know, that's why I'm saying. If they
can take from a בהמה, behemah, they can take from.
That's exactly what I was saying. Like I don't understand the מציאות
metziut of that case. Right, that's what I was saying. I don't
understand it. I'm saying somehow they're knowing one but not the, you
know, but not the other.
Not everybody has cattle, but there's only one baker in town so
nobody's really up on the,
I know, but they don't know that the Roman, they don't know
that the Roman guy comes along and takes חלה. Challah.
Because he takes cattle because that's what he takes from everybody. There's
one baker in town, I'm just positing. If there's one baker in
town so nobody knows the tax law.
It could be. It could be. Okay, right. Everybody, fine. All right,
that then that makes sense. Right.
It could be. Yeah. Anyway, so that's the point.
So that was the ownership of a נכרי. nochri. Does that exempt
you from
certain
things or not? Oh, that's right. That's what
the
אית ליה קלא. it lei kala.
That's what Rav Papa said.
That's what the לית ליה קלא leit lei kala and אית ליה
קלא it lei kala means. What? אית ליה קלא. it lei kala.
No, no, of course, but how are they going to know whether
you took חלה Challah or not? You know what I mean?
That’s, because there’s one guy, that’s exactly right, that makes sense. There’s
one guy who’s going to know whether there's חלה...
Challah... Well, that’s a different question. Maybe רב פפא... Rav Pappa... How
does anybody know if you take חלה Challah in your kitchen?
Well, that’s my point. How... I don’t know how they’re going to
know whether or not you’ve taken, you know what I mean? Maybe
they’d look. That’s, that’s what I was saying.
How are they going to know? Even if you give a בכור.
bechor. Right, maybe.
I guess that’s also true.
Well, I imagine בכור bechor would probably have to be marked or
something like that.
Yeah, בכור bechor or מעשר. ma’aser.
Well,
the מעשר ma’aser is actually marked, you know, you put like a
red line, but the בכור bechor not as much.
Yeah, בכור bechor not... No, no.
All right, well let’s just go on because I certainly do want
to get to the end, talk a little bit about ביטול. bittul.
Along these lines, תנו רבנן נכרי שנכנס לחצרו של ישראל וחמצו בידו.
tanu rabanan nochri shenichnas l'chatzeiro shel yisrael v'chametzo
b'yado.
So he’s, you know, he’s coming into your house. You know, you’ve
cleaned it for פסח. Pesach.
And now he’s like cookies... Yeah. But אין זה זקוק לבער. ein
ze zakuk l'va'er. But you don’t have to get rid of it.
I mean, like you don’t have to, meaning you don’t have to
like say shoo, get out of here, what are you doing? You
know? It’s not your חמץ, Chametz, right?
So, I mean, you know, if he like would leave his cookie
like on a counter, maybe, you know, you might want to tell
him like don’t leave your cookie in the counter, but you don’t
have to like get rid of them, you know what I mean?
You don’t have to get rid of the חמץ chametz, like now,
you know, throw it in the garbage right now. It’s not yours.
That’s the point.
However, הפקידו אצלו זקוק לבער. hifkido etzlo zakuk l'va'er. If he’s מפקיר...
mafkir... if he’s מפקיד mafkid this חמץ chametz by you, then you
do need to get rid of it.
Which so far, you know, something not new. But ייחד לו בית.
yicheid lo bayit. So what do we mean by that? ייחד לו
בית yicheid lo bayit what רש''י Rashi says this means, he says
is that it’s not like... he didn’t... it doesn’t necessarily mean he
gives him his own house, but like, you know, it means like
his own space. And what he’s saying is, yeah, no, it’s fine,
you know, go ahead, put it wherever you want, right? That’s basically
what he’s saying. Then אין זה זקוק לבער. ein ze zakuk l'va'er.
You know, you don’t have to get rid of it. But the
way רש''י Rashi explains it is that because by me saying that,
I’m not מקבל אחריות. mekabel achrayut. And that’s the whole point, right?
I’ve got to get rid of it if it’s my אחריות achrayut
and if it’s not my אחריות achrayut then it’s considered the non-Jew’s
חמץ. chametz And then that’s...
You can put it down anywhere you want, but if the dog
eats it don’t blame me.
Right.
So רש''י Rashi says that that’s the issue, whether I’m מקבל אחריות
mekabel achrayut on it or not.
תוספות Tosafot doesn’t agree.
He’s saying even if I was
מקבל אחריות, mekabel achrayut, even in אחריות, achrayut, I’m responsible but I’m
telling him put it wherever you want.
So, and then שנאמר לא ימצא. shene'emar lo yimatze. מאי קאמר? ma
ka'amar?
What does he mean by this? אמר רב פפא ארישא קאי. amar
rav pappa areisha ka'i. You know it doesn’t go on the end.
והכי קאמר: v'hachi ka'amar: הפקידו אצלו זקוק לבער. hifkido etzlo zakuk l'va'er.
If he’s מפקיד mafkid the חמץ chametz. by me, I have to
be diligent to get rid of it שנאמר לא ימצא. shene'emar lo
yimatze. That’s what he’s saying, right? That’s why I’ve got to get
rid of it because לא ימצא. lo yimatze. Because if he’s... if
he is מפקיד mafkid it and I am accepting responsibility, then as
we’ve mentioned before it’s considered mine. And if it’s mine, then it’s
a problem of לא ימצא. lo yimatze. So that’s why I’ve got
to get rid of it. It’s not going on the second case
because the second case when he isn’t accepting responsibility, at least according
to רש''י, Rashi, so then certainly it wouldn’t be a problem of
לא ימצא. lo yimatze. So... so לא ימצא lo yimatze is going
on the first part where it is a problem. רב אשי אמר
לעולם אסיפא קאי. rav ashi amar l'olam aseifa ka'i. No, actually he’s
going on the second part. So how do we interpret that? והכי
קאמר: v'hachi ka'amar: ייחד לו בית אין זקוק לבער.
yicheid lo bayit
ein zakuk l'va'er. Right, they don’t have to get rid of it.
Because כשנאמר לא ימצא בבתיכם. ke'shene'emar lo yimatze b'vateichem. Because it says
לא ימצא lo yimatze and then and then it’s not a problem.
והא לאו דידיה הוא. v'ha lav dideih hu. It’s not... and it’s
not mine. It’s the נכרי’s. nochri נכרי כי קא עייל לביתו דנפשיה
קא עייל. nochri ki ka ayyil l'veito d'nafsheih ka ayyil. So,
and this is a very interesting statement because the נכרי nochri is
going into my house to get his חמץ chametz as if he’s
going to his house. What does that mean he’s going to his
house? It’s my house. No, what we’re basically saying is that it’s...
it’s considered his house because what I’m essentially doing in this case
is what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that is that I’m
actually שוכר socher him, like as if I’m שוכר socher him this...
wherever the space is that he’s going to put it in, that
space is his. So when he’s going into the house, he’s going
to the part of the house that’s his, essentially. That’s what it
seems to be saying.
Is he taking possession with a קנין kinyan of that area?
Oh, that’s a... that’s a very good question. And we’re actually going
to talk about that right now. How is this... how is this
exactly working? Or we’re going to sort of talk about it right
now.
Just give me a second.
So, yeah, I mean, how did you read והא לאו דידיה הוא?
v'ha lav dideih hu?
So, okay, so ייחד לו בית. yicheid lo bayit. I’ll read it
again. If I tell him, you know, pick a spot, I’m not
זקוק לבער zakuk l'va'er because it says לא
ימצא בבתיכם. lo yimatze b'vateichem. It cannot be found in your homes.
your homes is in me the Jew home. והאי לאו lav, דידיהו
*v'hai lav dideihu*. And this חמץ chametz *chametz* is not considered mine,
me the Jew, because I didn't accept the responsibility for it. דנוכרי
כי קא עייל *d'nochri ki ka ayil* when the נוכרי *nochri* brings
the חמץ chometz *chametz* into the house, and when he comes back
into the house to get it, לביתי דנפשי קא עייל *l'veitei d'nafshei
ka ayil*.
He's, the נוכרי *nochri* is bringing it in or taking it out
whatever of his, the נוכריס *nochri's* own house. It's not my house.
It's not בתיכם *bateichem* of my house; it's his house. Which is
what I'm saying the implication is is that since he has the
right to deposit, or I'm giving him the right now to deposit
the חמץ chometz *chametz* some place in my house,
then he, it's sort of like his house. He has rights to
the house so to speak.
So what happens
if he brings חמץ chametz, *chametz* into the Jewish house?
Yeah, well if he just is coming in there and I'm not
accepting any responsibility whatsoever and he's just coming because
it's his חמץ chametz *chametz*.
And he can eat in the Jewish home?
He can eat in the Jewish home.
Or
deposit. Now you might not be so happy about having חמץ chametz,
*chametz*, but technically it's not actually a problem.
You mean my woman can buy a roll and eat חמץ chametz
*chametz* on פסח Pesach *Pesach*?
Apparently, I mean we don't want her to use your dishes, right?
But she buys a
sandwich outside she can bring into the house.
That's what this is saying. I'm not פסקנינג *paskening* here, but that's
what this is saying right now.
I'll advise her not to do it.
No, but you know what's really interesting also? Let's say Jewish schools,
let's say the school or שול *shul* is open on פסח Pesach,
*Pesach* and the maintenance staff
wants to have lunch.
It's very hard to say to them, no you can't go out
and only bring in כשר *kosher* food; it's very expensive for them.
So you can designate a place for them to eat.
You designate a place for them, but according to this, you would
be okay for them to come into the building with the חמץ
chametz *chametz* in their space, they're sitting in their office but they're
eating חמץ chametz? *chametz* in the שול *shul* building on פסח Pesach,
*Pesach*. According to this, it's not a problem.
Because I told him מצה *matzah* only מצה *matzah* to eat.
Yeah, according to this it's not a problem.
We'll have to
ask
Rabbi Libby.
I mean, what you don't want to do though is tell her
to keep so much חמץ chametz? *chametz*, let's say on your countertop
in the open because then you may come to eat it. That's
a separate problem, right?
But rabbi, your rabbi is this the הלכה halakha *halacha*?
That's true, I am a rabbi.
I'm not sure what the הלכה *halacha* is.
But what we're saying right now though is that if I'm giving
him a place, then he sort of has if you will rights
to the house. He
has rights to the house
and so that's not considered my house vis-a-vis this איסור issur *issur*
of חמץ chametz *chametz*.
Charlie, you know the apocryphal story about the רבנית *rebbetzin* who, the
rabbi was telling her, listen you don't have to do so much
for cleaning for פסח Pesach *Pesach*, you don't have to do this,
you don't have to do that, and she says listen, you and
your שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* would be eating חמץ chametz, *chametz* on
פסח Pesach *Pesach*.
Right.
Yeah, you're טרייפינג *treifing* up my house. So
that's
what we're saying right now.
But then, okay fine, but the implication is,
so למימרא דשכירות קניא *l'meimra d'shchirus kanya*, this is a שכירות *shchirus*
question. So basically,
so this works? So just like that? We're good? So now he's
becoming like if you will like an owner of this property. But
ותנן אף במקום שאמרו להשכיר לא לבית דירה אמרו מפני שמכניסין לתוכו
עבודת גילולים *v't'nan af b'makom she'amru l'haskir lo l'veit dira amru mipnei
shemachnisin l'tocho avodat gilulim*. So ואי סלקא דעתך דשכירות קניא כי קא
עייל לביתי דנפשי קא עייל *v'i salka dach'tach dishchirus kanya ki ka
ayil l'veitei d'nafshei ka ayil*. So that'd be a problem. You know,
even in a case that we said that I just, although this
is sort of, we don't want to really rent houses to the
עובדי כוכבים *ovdei kochavim* to begin with. And I'm not going into
that right now. But even a case where they're saying you're allowed
to, we didn't let you do it for a בית דירה beise
dira *beit dira* to actually live there. We let you do it
to,
whatever, keep your animals there, storage space exactly, that kind of stuff.
And the reason why we don't want it to be a בית
דירה *beit dira* is because they're going to be, then okay, then
he's going to bring his idol in there and we don't want
idols,
in what could be construed as being your house.
So that'd be a problem, right? But now if you're saying שכירות
קניא sekhirut kanya *shchirus kanya*, now if we're saying that vis-a-vis the
חמץ chametz *chametz* it's his house, you're not allowed to do that.
We just said a second ago you're not allowed to give it
to him as a בית דירה *beit dira*. But we're saying this
is exactly what happens in the case where you let him have
a place in your house for חמץ chametz *chametz*. It's considered his
house, which is why it's not a problem for you. But then
we decided no that you're not allowed to rent it to him
as a house because of
concern
of idolatry.
Essentially analogy because the presumably the נכרי nachri is also forbidden for
idolatry? For idolatry? That's what I'm saying.
Yeah, yeah, but I guess we're saying practically it's what he's going
to do.
Yeah. Yeah.
No.
So how's this working? So שאני הכא shani hacha so sort of
the same answer דאפקיה רחמנא בלשון לא ימצא. de'afke rakhamana bilshon lo
yimatsei.
So it's a little bit different. מי שמצוי בידך mi-she-matsui beyadekha יצא
זה שאינו מצוי בידך. ye-yatsei zeh she-eino matsui beyadekha.
So that's again you know it could have said a whole bunch
of ways of constructing the איסור חמץ isur chometz where it says
לא ימצא. lo yimatsei. So now לא ימצא lo yimatsei
on surface level can say
it can't be found, right? But what it also means like almost
like מזומן, mezuman, has to be מצוי בידך, matsui beyadekha, has to
be something that like you know you can easily have, it's yours
and you know just like whatever, I can take it easily, right?
But in this case it's I can't take it easily because it's
his. So let's forget about the בית דירה for a second.
What what we're basically saying is is
this חמץ chametz is not considered you know readily accessible to me.
So we're not you know so the spot that he's putting it
in is is not
does not actually belong to him, at least according to what רש"י
Rashi is saying, we're retreating from that initial assumption.
But rather what he's saying is I'm just not accepting any responsibility
for it.
So basically so therefore the reason why I'm not חייב chayav is
because I'm not accepting responsibility for it. There are other questions on
that but
it's not that the whole house belongs to him but that according
to רש"י Rashi
that cabinet...
No, but now we're saying not really.
שאין מצוי בידך שהרי אותה זוית מסורה לנכרי.
she-ein
matsui
beyadekha she-harei otah zavit mesurah lenokhri.
Right,
but then the problem is that yes, but he's not I mean
it is but it isn't. Like we're saying it's מסורה mesura but
it's not that he owns it. You know what I mean? Because
if you know if we're saying that he owns it, then then
I don't look I'm having a hard time with that. I actually
really think that the point is that it's not
belonging
to him but designated for his use. See, that's otherwise this wouldn't
make sense, you know?
So it's not שכירה, sekhira, it's not that it's שכירה sekhira to
him, but it is
somehow a right to use, but doesn't make it
mine, or not your obligation to it, in other words some middle
position.
Yeah, I mean it's what I'm saying, it's a little bit
we're
sort of like you know cutting it I don't want to say
splitting hairs, but yeah, I mean some again like it's we've said
a second before that if it would be שכירה sekhira it would
be a problem, right? But somehow this isn't a שכירה sekhira issue
and it's not considered מצוי. matsui. Why is it not considered מצוי?
matsui? It's hard to understand why. Because like first of all I'm
not accepting responsibility for it. If I was accepting responsibility for it,
then I mean that's really the gist of it, and essentially I'm
not accepting responsibility for it, because if I were, then that would
be the problem. Now how do you do
שכירות קניא sekhirut kanya here specifically means to a non-Jew. I'm sorry?
שכירות קניא here specifically the issue here.
Yeah, the issue here is to the non-Jew. Then we get into
all these other issues,
like Charlie said, a קנין kinyan with a non-Jew
through שכירה. sekhira.
Right, so somehow it's not I'm
at least according to רש"י Rashi we've constructed the case such that
I'm not accepting responsibility for it, but yet it's not and it's
still considered his,
his as in the נכרי's. nochri,
And you know but he picked the spot. So but he picked
the spot which entitles him to you know to use the spot,
but it somehow doesn't give him a תפיסה tfisa in my house,
right? I guess it's just viewing as he has rights to use
the spot and just to use the spot, but it's we've retreated
by saying it's like he's going to his house. We're not saying
it's not like he's going to his own house. It's like it's
not considered מצוי בידי matsui beyadi because I didn't accept the responsibility.
That's really what that's like the thrust of it. Do you understand
what I'm trying to say there? How you work out the particulars,
you know does he own the spot, does he not own the
spot, you know does he have rights to the spot but not
owning it. The point is though it's not I've not accepted responsibility.
That's the main point of רש"י. Rashi.
So basically he owns it, it wouldn't be and it would be
like a rental, like a renter in an apartment.
Okay. גופא Gufa אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav: המוציא חמץ בביתו ביום טוב Hamotsei chametz bevaito beyom tov this
is the הלכה כופה עליו כלי. kofeh alav keli. Right? So let's
say it is פסח Pesach and you know did my best to
get rid of everything, nevertheless I you know open up my cabinet
and lo and behold there is something. Now the חמץ chametz on
יום טוב yom tov is מוקצה muktseh so I can't do anything
with it, I can't burn it either. So what I do is
I cover it, you know I cover it because... Don't want to
just like we did with the שרצים sheratzim in the Temple. It's
מוקצה, muktzeh, it's מוקצה, muktzeh, right? Because I have no use for
it, and also, you know, I don't want anyone to be eating
it.
And then afterwards I'll burn it. אמר רבא אם שהקדשו אינו צריך.
Amar Rava im shehekdesho eino tzarich. But but if this this is
like, you know, whole הקדש, hekdesh I'm מקידש makdish this a roll,
let's say, you know, then then I don't have to. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? מבדל בדילי מיניה. Mivdal bedili minei. I know enough to
separate it from it. הקדש hekdesh, is a big deal, I don't
want to I don't want to get near הקדש, hekdesh you know,
cooties so to speak, but you know what I'm saying, like I
know it's off limits. So,
you know, so I know enough. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב חמץ
של נכרי עושה לו מחיצה עשרה טפחים משום היכר. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav chametz shel nochri oseh lo mechitzah asarah tefachim mishum heker.
If it's if it's not הקדש hekdesh, חמץ chametz but rather non-Jewish
חמץ, chametz then I have to make I have to separate it.
So let's, you know, so it's not like you can just like
put it on my countertop or, you know, yeah, it should be
some place where, you know, it's it's yeah, I mean, so you
know, which is why like you know in our מכירת חמץ mechirat
chametz these days, you also say like, you know, where is it
really, right? You're supposed to really designate it its own place. המשנה
ברורה HaMishnah Berurah goes as far as says give them the key
to if it's in a cabinet, give if it's a lock, give
them the key to the cabinet, all that.
So if it's חמץ chametz... of a נכרי, separate it משום היכר.
mishum heker. ושל הקדש אינו צריך. Veshel hekdesh eino tzarich. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? מבדל בדיל אינש מיניה. Mivdal bedil inish minei. Same thing
as with הקדש hekdesh stuff, I know enough not to approach it,
I'm going to keep my distance. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב המפרש
ויוצא בשיירא קודם שלשים יום אין זקוק לבער.
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav hameforesh veyozei beshayara kodem sheloshim yom ein
zakuk leva'er. So if I am going on, I'm going to see
there's a
מחלוקת. machloket. So if I'm going to be, you know, taking a
trip 30 days before the חג, chag, אין זקוק לבער. ein zakuk
leva'er. So now never remember, like you know, this is operating on
the principle of מן התורה ביטול min haTorah bitul is is enough,
right? But you know but we have an obligation to do ביטול,
bitul, I mean ביעור. biur.
Or if you say מן התורה ביעור min haTorah biur is enough,
or you know, one of them is enough, I don't have to
do both, right?
But the point being though, let's say let's say I do my
ביטול, bitul, if according to this position of רב, Rav,
I don't have to do you know the
need
for a ביעור biur kicks in within 30 days of the חג,
chag, and we're going to get to that, or potentially even or
just two weeks, you know, before.
So I don't have to actually מבער, meva'er, you know, I'm not
I see I'm not coming back, right? So what's, you know, what's
the problem? I've
already מבטל mevatel it, I'm not worried that like, you know, I'm
going to come let's say to eat it on פסח, Pesach, I'm
not even here. So you don't have to do anything about it.
המפרש ויוצא בשיירא קודם שלשים יום אין זקוק לבער.
Hameforesh veyozei beshayara kodem sheloshim yom ein
zakuk leva'er. However, תוך שלשים יום זקוק לבער. Toch sheloshim yom zakuk
leva'er. Within 30 days I do. אמר אביי הדין דאמרת תוך שלשים
יום זקוק לבער לא אמרן. Amar Abaye ha de'amart toch sheloshim yom
zakuk leva'er lo amaran. And he says even that within 30 days
I have to מבער, meva'er, אלא שדעתו לחזור. ella sheda'ato lachzor. It's
only when I'm going to come back. אבל אין דעתו לחזור אין
זקוק לבער.
Aval ein da'ato lachzor ein zakuk
leva'er.
Then I don't have to.
That means he might come back on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed?
Yes. So now this is going to we're going to get into
an interesting issue over
here that
you know
I'll I'll just do I'll just wait I'll get into it in
just a second. I'm just going to read the next position. אמר
ליה רבא
ואי דעתו לחזור אפילו מראש השנה נמי. Amar lei Rava ve'i da'ato
lachzor afilu merosh hashanah nami. Oh, if you're going to come back,
I have to get rid of it.
I don't care when you're leaving,
you're going to come back to חמץ, chametz, right?
Even מראש השנה, meRosh HaShanah,
you know,
six months earlier, you gotta get rid of it. אלא אמר רבא
הדין דאמרת קודם שלשים יום אין זקוק לבער. Ella amar Rava ha
de'amart kodem sheloshim yom ein zakuk leva'er. When are we saying that
you don't have to you know
before 30 days? לא אמרן אלא שאין דעתו לחזור. Lo amaran ella
she'ein da'ato lachzor. That's only if you're not you're not going to
come back. So basically we're saying is if you're within 30 days,
I don't really care, no matter what, you're going to have to
you're going to have to get rid of it.
Further than 30 days, if I'm going to come back, I have
to get rid of it. If I'm not going to come back,
I don't. That's essentially what רבא Rava is saying. אבל דעתו לחזור
אפילו מראש השנה זקוק לבער.
Aval da'ato lachzor afilu merosh
hashanah zakuk leva'er. ואזדא רבא לטעמיה דאמר רבא עושה ביתו אוצר. Ve'azda
Rava leta'ameih de'amar Rava oseh beito otzar. Basically the same similar case.
I'm making my my house into a storehouse, right? But so, you
know, I'm going to have חמץ chametz and then I'm going to
have other stuff, right? I'm storing my my bread and my
fruit, right? And and
so קודם שלשים יום אין זקוק לבער, kodem sheloshim yom ein zakuk
leva'er, תוך שלשים יום זקוק לבער. toch sheloshim yom zakuk leva'er. וקודם
שלשים יום נמי לא אמרן אלא שאין דעתו לפנותו, Vekodem sheloshim yom
nami lo amaran ella she'ein da'ato lefanoto, right? Meaning like I'm not,
you know, basic same idea as getting back to it, you know,
let's say the חמץ chametz is
buried, it's all the way on the bottom. So, you know, I'm
not going to clean out this
אוצר. otzar. אבל דעתו לפנותו אפילו קודם שלשים יום נמי זקוק
לבער.
Aval da'ato lefanoto afilu kodem sheloshim
yom nami zakuk leva'er. Same idea. So what he basically says is
that, you know, if I'm going to come back, then no matter
when I go, I have to get rid of it because I'm
coming back. But if I'm not going to come back, then if
it's further out 30 days or further,
then I don't have to worry about it. Now you know רש"י
Rashi makes a very interesting point. So like what's the problem? So
let's say I come back.
So what's the... What's the what's the problem? Let's just look at
this רש"י Rashi דאפילו בראש השנה נמי dafilu b'Rosh Hashanah nami which
is four lines from the bottom דכי הדר ביה בימי הפסח עבר
עליה.
dechi hadar bei b'yemei hapesach
avar alei.
When I come back, I'm over on it. I mean, I transgress.
והיא שעת הביעור דבטלו. vehi sha'at habiur debatlo. Now once I come
back on פסח, Pesach. it's too late. You know, it's not mine
anymore. שהרי איסור הנאה הוא ואינו שלו. sheharei issur hana'ah hu veino
shelo.
It's איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. It's not mine anymore and I'll explain
this in a second. וכל הרואהו עובר עליו. vechol haro'eihu over alav.
And when I see it, I'm over on it. So really? So
basically what we're trying to say, and we're going to say more
of this on the עמוד ב amud beis which I hope we
get to, is that it's very interesting. So you know once פסח
Pesach? starts, am I allowed to eat חמץ? chametz No, of course
not, right? Am I allowed to have הנאה hana'ah from חמץ? No,
I can't have any הנאה hana'ah from it. So
what's interesting is then what you would say is logically, if it's
an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah,
and the basically, and this is the position that איסור הנאה, issur
hana'ah, the תורה Torah basically takes it out of your possession.
It's not mine anymore.
Once, so then how am I over on it on בל יראה
ובל ימצא? bal yira'eh uval yimatzei? Okay, so the תורה Torah is
saying even though it's איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, it is considered mine
enough to be over בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yira'eh uval yimatzei.
I mean obviously, otherwise there's no איסור בל יראה ובל ימצא. issur
bal yira'eh uval yimatzei. It's written it out of existence if we
say איסור הנאה issur hana'ah is not mine anymore and the תורה
Torah is basically. So but the point, so what רש"י Rashi is
saying is I can't מבטל mevatel it on פסח Pesach because the
תורה Torah takes it out of my possession in so far as
giving me rights to מבטל mevatel it.
And then you know when I come back, not the moment I
see it, I mean because you know it's we're really worried about
is that I might hesitate, right? Now if I'm hesitating, alright now
I'm sort of trying to get it back, right? So during that
point, you know, meaning if I'm just you know the moment I
see it oh no, you know, it's not like you know you're
entering a house of like טומאה, tumah, you know what I mean?
It's like not not like you know
you got some time. It doesn't mean when he sees, the moment
he sees it he's going to be over. The moment he sees
it and does nothing about it. That's the way the מפרשים meforshim
explain this.
So what's interesting is תוספות Tosafot on another דף daf
says that actually believe it or not, that if I keep even
if it's פסח Pesach. and I find this חמץ and I don't
get rid of it right away, I keep it in the house
for a few days, I keep it in the house the entire
פסח, Pesach. I'm not over on it as long as I burn
it before the end of פסח. Pesach That's תוספות's Tosafot position.
Why? Because this is a separate concept of לאו הניתק לעשה, lav
hanitak la'aseh, right? Because there's a there's a
לאו, lav
I can't have חמץ, but הניתק לעשה hanitak la'aseh because תשביתו. tashbitu.
תשביתו Tashbitu is an עשה. aseh. אך ביום הראשון תשביתו. Ach bayom
harishon tashbitu. I can get rid of it. So basically since it's
one of these things, I can do a positive action, as long
as I do this positive action, I'm okay. If I haven't done
the positive action, then the לאו lav kicks in. So that's the
position of
תוספות. Tosafot.
And לאו הניתק לעשה, lav hanitak la'aseh, that principle is only to
determine whether you get מלקות, malkut, isn't it?
But apparently according to right because because לוקין על הלאו, lokin al
halav, but apparently over here too it's at least for תוספות's Tosafot
position is not that, that I'm not over on the לאו lav.
at all, not just vis-a-vis
מלקות. malkut. Alright fine, so then why do we need to do
ביטול bitul before פסח? Pesach Since you know as long as I
get rid of it, right? So what would the point be? So
according we would say or at least the position is advanced that
since I mean burning חמץ requires you got to do something, right?
You know, you mean maybe you need to get the wood and
you need to make a fire. So
the רבנן Rabanan would fear that you'd delay burning it until you
get the wood and then it's going to take a while and
then you could forget to burn it altogether.
So you know then
so in this case I mean you can't, תוספות Tosafot would still
agree you can't do the ביטול bitul on פסח Pesach because the
תורה Torah takes that out of your רשות reshut vis-a-vis ownership and
that, but you may not and then you may not get rid
of it before the end of פסח. Pesach So that's why you
have to מבטל mevatel your חמץ before פסח. Pesach As to the
mechanics of how ביטול bitul works, I'm going to hopefully get into
that on the עמוד ב amud beis if if I can. Okay,
anyway so now we just mentioned this whole this whole point that
the איסור issur, kicks in within a you know not the איסור,
issur the need to get rid of the חמץ to do ביעור
biur kicks in within a month, right? But that seems rather arbitrary.
How do we know a month, right? Since this is potential rabbinic
anyway?
And רבא Rava changed his position and adopt the principle of דעתו
לחזור אינו דעתו לחזור? da'ato lachazor eino da'ato lachazor?
Well he always has a...
but that was אביי Abaye that introduced that.
No because what אביי Abaye says...
And it's
more
than thirty days. שלושים יום. Shloshim Yom. So
now the question is
why thirty? שלושים יום מאי טעמיה? Shloshim yom mai ta'ameih? כדתניא שואלים
ודורשים
בהלכות פסח קודם לפסח שלושים יום.
Kedetanya sho'alin vedorshin
behilchot
Pesach kodem laPesach shloshim yom. So
basically
the point is now you're within the context of Pesach, you're in
the ambit, or whatever you'd like to say, of Pesach because within
thirty days you've got to be talking about Pesach anyway. So that's
why we have this thirty days. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר שתי
שבתות. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer shtei shabbatot. He says no, two
weeks, not thirty days. Okay fine. מאי טעמא
דתנא קמא? Mai ta'ama detanna kamma? How do we get thirty days?
That's the Tanna kamma position. שהרי משה עומד בפסח ראשון ומזהיר על
פסח שני. Sheharei Moshe omed bePesach Rishon umazhir al Pesach Sheini. Right?
Because that's how you get thirty days. שנאמר ויעשו בני ישראל את
הפסח. Shene'emar veya'asu venei Yisrael et haPasach. Pesach, Pasach,
I'm not sure which one it was. It's a.? I don't know.
Anyway,
no it's. Okay. את הפסח במועדו. Et haPasach bemo'ado.
And so Moshe was told by Hashem that they need to do
the Pesach in its appointed time. וכתיב ויהי אנשים אשר היו טמאים
לנפש אדם ולא יכלו לעשות הפסח ביום ההוא. Uchtiv vayehi anashim asher
hayu teme'im lenefesh adam velo yachlu la'asot haPesach bayom hahu. And they
went to Moshe then Moshe tells them about the פסח שני. Pesach
Sheini.
So that's what he says. So okay fine. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So okay, so why doesn't רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel accept this position? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אמר לך איידי דאיירי במילי דפסחא מסיק להו לכל מילי דפסחא. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel amar lach aidi de'airi bemillei dePascha massik lehu lechol
millei dePascha. Now
okay
fine, that's just because they came to him and they said, all
right, well it's Pesach Rishon, we're tamei, what do we do? So
he really could have just told them, all right just don't give
the Pesach now. Then he could have told them let's say two
weeks later, do a Pesach Sheini, because it's not like you need
to do much preparation for Pesach Sheini. But he just happened to
tell them right then because they're asking about Pesach. But for the
rest of us,
we don't need to. Two weeks will suffice. It's not like we
had a special case that necessitated a teaching of a special law,
which then caused Moshe to teach them about Pesach Sheini.
For the rest of us, two weeks will suffice. Okay fine. מאי
טעמא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Mai ta'ama deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel? Where
does he get two weeks from? שהרי משה עומד בראש חודש ומזהיר
על הפסח. Sheharei Moshe omed beRosh Chodesh umazhir al haPesach.
Because back to פרשת בא. Parshat Bo. שנאמר החודש הזה לכם ראש
חודשים ראשון הוא לכם לחודשי השנה. Shene'emar hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim
rishon hu lachem lechodshei hashanah. This is going to be ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. And then it says later, וכתיב דברו אל כל עדת
בני ישראל לאמר בעשור לחודש הזה ויקחו להם איש שה לבית אבות
שה לבית. Uchtiv dabru el kol adat benei Yisrael lemor be'asor lachodesh
hazeh veyikechu lahem ish seh leveit avot seh labayit. So he's already
telling them on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh to...
Hashem is telling Moshe on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh to tell בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael that this Pesach thing, this holiday called Pesach, is
coming up right after ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. But the question is
though, okay fine, that's when Hashem told Moshe, but how do we
know that Moshe told בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael on ראש חודש? Rosh
Chodesh? So that's the Gemara's question. ממאי דבריש ירחא קאי? Mimmay devereish
yarcha ka'i? How do we know that Moshe then told the Jewish
people on ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? דילמא בארבעה בירחא או בחמישה בירחא
קאי? Dilma be'arba'ah beyarcha o bechamishah beyarcha ka'i?
Maybe it could have been later, fourth, fifth day. Anyway, the truth
of the matter is
that for that matter even Moshe telling the בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael,
you could even say that the question is that when did Hashem
tell Moshe? It just says that he told him החודש הזה לכם
ראש חודשים, Hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim,
and then which you would think though would be
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, telling him on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but
not necessarily. He could have told him on the fourth, fifth of
Nissan. By the way, this month we're in right now
is going to be the first month of the year.
That's a stretch.
Okay. But then we're going to try again. אלא אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק משמיה דרבינא מהכא. Ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mishmeih
deRavina mehacha. Fine, even if you accept the validity of this objection.
אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק משמיה דרבינא מהכא. Ela amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak mishmeih deRavina mehacha.
Okay, another pasuk. וידבר ה' אל משה במדבר סיני בשנה השנית בחודש
הראשון. Vayedabber Hashem el Moshe bemidbar Sinai bashanah hashenit bachodesh harishon.
Hashem spoke to Moshe in מדבר סיני Midbar Sinai in the second
year in the first month. וכתיב ויעשו בני ישראל את הפסח במועדו.
Uchtiv veya'asu benei Yisrael et haPesach bemo'ado. So that
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael do the Pesach.
And then the same question. הכא נמי ממאי דבריש ירחא קאי?
Hacha nami mimmay devereish
yarcha ka'i? And this is at least a better question on it.
It doesn't say anywhere that it's ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. He just
said it some time in that month. How do we know it
was ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? Which means if it's not ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, you don't have your two weeks. דילמא בארבעה בירחא
בחמישה בירחא קאי?
Dilma be'arba'ah beyarcha bechamishah
beyarcha ka'i? So maybe it's some point in the middle of the
month, or the beginning of the month, whatever. So אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. No, it is ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. How do we know? Because again, we're going to do
a bunch of hekeshim. אתיא מדבר ממדבר. Atya midbar mimmidbar. דכתיב הכא
במדבר סיני. Dechtiv hacha bemidbar Sinai. וכתיב התם וידבר ה' אל משה
במדבר סיני. Uchtiv hatam vayedabber Hashem el Moshe bemidbar Sinai.
This is the very beginning of במדבר. Bemidbar. וידבר ה' אל משה
במדבר סיני. Vayedabber Hashem el Moshe bemidbar Sinai. באוהל מועד באחד לחודש
השני be-Ohel Moed be-Echad la-Chodesh ha-Sheni on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
So that's in the במדבר. Midbar. מה להלן בראש חודש אף כאן
בראש חודש,
ma hallan be-Rosh Chodesh af
kan be-Rosh Chodesh,
right? So this is all במדבר. Ba-Midbar. So just like השם Hashem
spoke to משה Moshe in the beginning of ספר במדבר Sefer Ba-Midbar
in the במדבר Midbar on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and He told
them he needed to do the census, so too the במדבר Midbar
of the other פסוק, pasuk, וידבר השם אל משה במדבר סיני Vayidaber
Hashem el Moshe be-Midbar Sinai about doing the פסח Pesach was also
on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So we compare במדבר, Midbar, we basically
say just we're using the word במדבר Midbar like a גזירה שוה
gezeira shava again. So the פסח Pesach? part which comes, which...
the פסח Pesach part which is the first month, right? Although it's
mentioned later in the
תורה, Torah, is, mentions the word במדבר. be-Midbar. It doesn't say exactly
when it was spoken to, but we do know the beginning of
במדבר Ba-Midbar was said on
a ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So just like the במדבר Midbar
statement was on a first of a month, so too the במדבר
Midbar statement regarding פסח Pesach? mentioned later was also on the first
of a month. So and as we know, פסח Pesach. was two
weeks later. So that's how רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel gets his two weeks. Are we good with that?
I don't find it convincing, but keep going.
Okay, well, no, I mean, okay, I at least explained
it, whether or not you're convinced by it, okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara is actually going... now the גמרא Gemara is
saying, hey, wait a minute. When does במדבר Ba-Midbar open? במדבר Ba-Midbar
open as we just read,
וידבר השם אל משה במדבר סיני באוהל מועד באחד לחודש השני. Vayidaber
Hashem el Moshe be-Midbar Sinai be-Ohel Moed be-Echad la-Chodesh ha-Sheni. ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh of the second month. And פסח Pesach. though is mentioned
later. And when is פסח? Pesach פסח Pesach. is the first month,
right?
So why is it out of order? Is what the גמרא Gemara
question is. Why mention something that happened in the second month before
something happened in the first month? I mean, it's not... that's not
proving the two weeks or not, but it's just a side question.
So the גמרא Gemara question is ויכתוב ברישא דחודש ראשון והדר נכתוב
דחודש שני. ve-yichtov be-resha de-chodesh rishon ve-hadar yichtov de-chodesh sheni. Why is
it out of order? Why don't we just start במדבר Ba-Midbar talking
about פסח? Pesach.
Why don't they first mention the first month and then the second
month?
Why are we out of order? אמר רב מנשיא בר תחליפא משמיה
דרב זאת אומרת אין מוקדם ומאוחר בתורה.
Amar Rav Menashia bar Tachlipa mishmeih de-Rav Zot Omeret Ein Mukdam
u-Meuchar ba-Torah. From here we learn that, you know, that the תורה
Torah is not constrained by chronology essentially.
That's essentially what we mean by that.
So now we're going to see how far that holds. אמר רב
פפא לא אמרן אלא בתרי ענייני. Amar Rav Papa lo amran ela
be-trei inyanei.
That's only by two separate things, like we have over here, like,
you know, one, the beginning of במדבר Ba-Midbar is talking about counting
the Jewish people, and then later on it's talking about פסח. Pesach
So then the תורה Torah is not going to be מקיפד makpid
to be in order. אבל בחד עניינא מאי דמוקדם מוקדם ומאי דמאוחר
מאוחר.
aval be-chad inyana mai
de-mukdam mukdam ve-mai de-meuchar meuchar. But if you're like dealing with one
topic, you know, then there is a chronology. Don't just say like,
you know, if you're talking about the same topic throughout, don't just
say
that the first thing happened later and the second thing happened earlier.
Like, you know, say you're talking about a few פסוקים, pesukim, right?
We have the integrity of עניינים. inyanim. So within one עניין, inyan,
then there is a מוקדם ומאוחר. mukdam u-meuchar. ואי לא
תימא הכי, ve-ee lo tema hachi, if you don't say that, כלל
ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. klal u-prat ein bi-chlal ela mah
she-bi-prat. How do we have any of these hermeneutical principles? Right? We
have something called a כלל klal and a פרט, prat, right? And
in that order. So then the כלל klal is defined by what's
in the פרט. prat. How do we know it's a כלל ופרט?
klal u-prat? דילמא פרט וכלל הוא? dilma prat u-chlal hu? Maybe the
פרט prat came first, right? If you're saying there's no order, then
all rules are up for grabs. There's no rule, right? The rule
is if there's a כלל klal and then there's a פרט, prat,
meaning the כלל klal comes first and then the פרט prat comes
second, right? Then you can say that you learn that the כלל
klal is really defined by its פרט. prat. But if you're saying
though that there's no order, then maybe the פרט prat came first
and the כלל klal came second.
Yeah, okay, but actually that's true. All these rules are completely arbitrary
and the way you see a certain section of text as the
כלל klal as opposed to the פרט prat of something else is
hermeneutically very open-ended. So it's like a phenomenally postmodern discussion. It's like
an amazing discussion. They're like, okay, the ball stops here. The כללים
klalim are going to be the כללים klalim and the פרטים pratim
are going to be the פרטים. pratim. Otherwise, you wouldn't have any
objectivity. Well, they know that there's no objectivity, that's precisely why they
raise this discussion.
Yeah, right. In other words, they know that you can read the
text any way you want to read the text.
Well, we clearly don't want to.
No, so they say you can't because they know you can. So
they say you're not allowed to.
And then there's this dispute which we're not going to cover here
between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael over whether
the כלל ופרט klal u-prat even is the way to properly...
and ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u-mi'ut also. There are other ways of even
doing that. The whole thing is a... ותו פרט וכלל נעשה כלל
מוסיף על הפרט. ve-tu prat u-chlal na'asa klal mosif al ha-prat.
Same idea. And if you have a פרט prat and a כלל,
klal, then the כלל klal is adding onto the פרט. prat. How
do you know which is which? דילמא כלל, dilma klal, maybe the
כלל klal came first, you know, כלל ופרט הוא. klal u-prat hu.
So then, okay, then אי הכי אפילו בתרי ענייני נמי. ee hachi
afilu be-trei inyanei nami. You can say this about תרי ענייני! trei
inyanei! Why תרי ענייני trei inyanei it'll work? Same thing! אין
מוקדם ומאוחר בתורה,
Ein mukdam u-meuchar
ba-Torah, why
should you say it's תרי ענייני? trei inyanei?
הניחא למאן דאמר כלל ופרט
מרוחקין
זה מזה אין דנין
אותו בכלל ופרט שפיר.
Hanicha leman de-amar klal u-frat meruchakin zeh
mi-zeh ein
danin oto be-klal u-frat shapir.
אלא למאן דאמר דנין
מאי
איכא
למימר?
Ela le-man de-amar danin mai
ika le-meimar?
So the answer is אפילו למאן דאמר דנין הני מילי בחד עניינא
אבל בתרי ענייני אין דנין. afilu le-man de-amar danin hanei milei be-chad
inyana aval be-trei inyanei ein danin. All right, it's only so far
we're gonna let you take it, essentially, is what is what we're
saying. So,
you know, look,
it comes down to what you're saying in the end, you know,
that if it's two different passages, then we're not going to say
that, you know,
a כלל klal and a פרט. prat. So are we okay with
that? Do I need to show
your objection that בחד עניינא be-chad inyana with כלל ופרט klal u-frat
and so on, they do stick to the order in which it's
put. They do. Why are you saying it's arbitrary?
Because underlying this whole discussion, in my opinion, I think, is the
fact that they know that it is that the just as there,
in other words, you can say that the פסוקים psukim in any
one עניין inyan are also out of order. Why not?
Well, that's exactly his point. בחד עניינא, be-chad inyana, you have to
say.
Why do you have to? You don't have to. They're saying with
that, we're going to establish the ground rules by definition right now.
It's not there's no it's not מוכרח muchrach that it has to
be. Doesn't have to be.
Given that we have all these principles of כלל ופרט, klal u-frat,
and they wouldn't they be able to operate in a but so
the fine.
So they're going to say, listen guys, we know that the text
intrinsically will the text itself will intrinsically accept any approach to reading
it. We're going to establish the rules of how we want to
read it. There's tremendous tension underneath that. That's all I'm saying. In
other words, I'm not saying we should read the Torah differently than
the חכמים, Chachamim, חס וחלילה, chas ve-chalila, they've imposed rules. You have
a field out there. Okay, we're going to play baseball. You're going
to hit the ball when I pitch it to you. You could
run to third base first. No, but then we are defining that's
not baseball. That's not baseball. You have to run to the right.
You can't. Could you theoretically? All I've got is the field and
some markers on the field. Yeah, you could have done anything you
wanted. We're going to define that baseball that's not baseball, that's something
else if you run to third base first. Okay, but they know
that it could have been the other way. They know it could
have been. That's what I like.
I think there
is like phenomenally there is so much intellectual tension, I think, underneath
this stuff.
Yeah.
Okay, we've just a few I I really want it's 8:27. Yes,
I really want to get to okay.
No, he's going to finish this עמוד. amud.
וגם. Ve-gam. And and I want to talk about this. This is
key stuff. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav,
first I'm going to say it, then we're going to discuss it.
הבודק צריך שיבטל. Ha-bodek tzarich she-yevatel.
So now you know, although מן התורה, min ha-Torah,
you've already mentioned that you can just do ביטול, bitul,
now you're also doing בדיקה, bedika, right? Okay, so you may have
thought that one or the other, right? If I do בדיקה, bedika,
then I don't need to do ביטול. bitul. If I do ביטול,
bitul, I don't need to do בדיקה. bedika. But no, nevertheless, הבודק
צריך שיבטל. ha-bodek tzarich she-yevatel. I still I still need to to
do it. But why? I mean like, you know, if I'm going
to get rid of everything, why do I have to do ביטול?
bitul? So מה טעמא? mai ta'ama? נימא משום פרורין? neima mishum perurin?
Maybe there are a few crumbs there. And that's the problem. הא
נינהו לא חשיבי. ha ninhu lo chashivi. That doesn't that's that's nothing.
It doesn't count against me essentially. You're not over בל יראה ובל
ימצא bal yera'eh u-val yimatzei for a few crumbs. I've you know,
a few crumbs is not it's not considered בל יראה. bal yera'eh.
I'm not really seeing anything. I've gotten rid of everything.
So מה טעמא? mai ta'ama? The איסור issur wouldn't kick in for
that. או וכי תימא כיון דמינטר להו אגב ביתיה חשיבי, O u-ve-chi
teima keivan de-minter lehu agav beiteih chashivi,
even if you're going to say that they somehow achieve significance because,
you know, just like I watch my house and now these crumbs
are in my house, they're now considered significant because of the larger
significance of my house, that doesn't work either. דתניא, De-tanya, סופי תאנים.
sofei te'enim.
Let's say I'm you know, there there are several seasons of the
of the תאנים te'enim harvest, let's say, right? So we're at the
end of the harvest, and you know, basically harvested everything except for
a few unripe figs. And
so that's not what I'm harvesting right now, but ומשמר שדהו מפני
ענבים, u-mishamer sadehv penei anavim, that's not what, you know, what I'm
really interested in, it's now it happens to be it's now in
the middle of grape season. So it's the end of fig season
and but it's, you know, full force of grape season, and I'm
watching my field מפני ענבים. penei anavim. או סופי ענבים ומשמר שדהו
מפני מקשאות ודלועות, O sofei anavim u-mishamer sadehv penei miksha'ot u-delu'ot, or
or it's really the end of grape season but you know, but
now it's like cucumber season, it's gourd season. Anyway, בזמן שבעל הבית
מקפיד עליהם אסורין משום גזל. be-zman she-ba'al ha-bayit makpid aleihem asurin mishum
gezel. If if I'm still מקפיד makpid on these remaining, you know,
either figs or grapes as the case may be, then אסורין משום
גזל וחייבין במעשר. asurin mishum gezel ve-chayavin be-ma'aser. They achieve significance. Someone
steals it, it's considered stealing. If I have to take מעשר ma'aser
from it. But however, בזמן שאין בעל הבית מקפיד עליהם מותרין משום
גזל ופטורין מן המעשר. be-zman she-ein ba'al ha-bayit makpid aleihem mutarin mishum
gezel u-pturin min ha-ma'aser. If I don't really care about it, then
actually someone can. apparently, הפקר hefker לאו.
So okay, but I'm surely not מקפיד maqpid on these crumbs, right?
Again, like you know, the figs are washed vis-a-vis something else, right?
The grapes. The grapes. גארני, gorni, I don't really care. I'm just
גארני gorni it. I'm not... it's being guarded אגב אורחיה agav orchia
and I don't really care about the פירוד. perud. Right. So I
don't care about it. So then why is that a problem? אמר
רבא Amar Rava this is key. אמר רבא Amar Rava גזירה שמא
ימצא גלוסקא יפה, gezeirah shema yimtza gluska yafa, the proverbial גלוסקא יפה.
gluska yafa. I'm going to find this nice roll, right? I basically
didn't do as good a search as I should have, right? You
know, I thought I got everything out. I didn't. I found this
and then דעתיה עילויה. daateih ilaveih. Now that's a very curious... I'll
talk about it in a second, but דעתיה עילויה, daateih ilaveih, my
mind will be on it. It's significant. I mean, it's a גלוסקא
יפה. gluska yafa. It's not a bagel.
It's a bagel.
Your כוונה kavanah shifts in that moment. It was not on my
mind at all. All of a sudden I come across this amazing
bagel.
Right, but the problem is, like, forget about my mind on it.
If then it's... forget it's... it should be בל יראה ובל ימצא.
bal yeira'eh uval yimatze. Forget about my דעת, daat, right? Why? Who
cares?
So but we'll talk about this in a second. But ובחי משכחת
לה לבטליה. uv'chai mashkachat lah l'vatlei. Okay, fine, so what? So I
find this nice גלוסקא. gluska. ובחי משכחת לה לבטליה. uv'chai mashkachat lah
l'vatlei. Let me just do ביטול. bitul.
No, because דילמא משכחת לה בתר איסורא. dilma mashkachat lah batar issura.
We're not talking about, let's say, ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, you know,
I'm finding it on פסח. Pesach So what? ולאו ברשותיה קיימא v'lav
birshuteih qayma דלא מצי לבטליה. d'la matzi l'vatlei. Now I... and it's
no longer considered my רשות reshut and I can't לבטליה. l'vatlei. אמר
רב אלעזר Amar Rav Elazar שני דברים אינם ברשותו של אדם. shnei
devarim einam birshuto shel adam. There are two things that are not
in the רשות reshut of a person because once פסח kicks in,
it's איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. It's not... it shouldn't be in my
possession, but nevertheless וחסכן הכתוב כאילו ברשותו. v'haschan hakatuv k'ilu birshuto. The
Torah is going to make me liable for it, ואלו הן v'elu
hen בור ברשות הרבים, bor birshut harabim, right, a pit in the
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Let's say I dig a pit in the
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. The רשות הרבים reshut harabim is not mine.
I don't own the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Nevertheless, I'm חייב hayyav
if, you know, an animal gets damaged in it. וחמץ משש שעות
ולמעלה v'chametz meshesh sha'ot ul'malah and חמץ once the איסור of it
kicks in, which is, you know, the sixth hour of פסח.
So since the חמץ I can't be מבטליה mevatlei because it's כאילו
ברשותי? k'ilu birshuti? What? According to רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, I can't
be מבטליה? mevatlei?
No, I can't be מבטליה mevatlei because it's no longer in my
רשות, reshut, but nevertheless I'm liable on בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal
yeira'eh uval yimatze.
Oh, כאילו k'ilu meaning I don't have אחריות achrayut but I'm liable
as if I did have אחריות. achrayut.
Correct. So therefore that would be a problem. I can't מבטלה. mevatlah.
So therefore I have to, you know, do ביטול. bitul. Now, let
me just talk a second about ביטול חמץ. bitul chametz. We've already
mentioned a lot about this before, I mean especially, you know, we've
had a משנה. mishnah. How does this work? Look at רש"י Rashi
for a second
and let me just find the רש"י Rashi that I want you
to see.
He talks about what you say for ביטול. bitul.
Here.
הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodeq tzarich sheyevatel. I'm going up a bit. It's
pretty much smack towards the middle of the רש"י. Rashis. You see
it? הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodeq tzarich sheyevatel. It's right across from תוספות
אבל, Tosafot Aval, basically. See תוספות אבל, Tosafot Aval, go across to
the רש"י. Rashi.
Okay, I got it. הבודק צריך שיבטל.
habodeq tzarich sheyevatel. That's the דיבור המתחיל. dibur hamatchil.
I'm going to read it. Across from אבל? Aval? תוספות אבל.
Tosafot Aval. There's two תוספות אבל. Tosafot Avals.
The first one.
Yeah, you're right. Good point. תוספות אבל, Tosafot Aval, הבודק צריך שיבטל
habodeq tzarich sheyevatel בלבו b'libo סמוך לבדיקה מיד, samuch l'vdika miyad, and
what do you say? ואומר כל חמירא דאיכא בביתא הדין ליבטל. v'omer
kol chamira d'ika b'veita hadein livatel. And that's it, right?
Now what is our נוסח? nusach?
כל חמירא
חמירא דאיתיה ברשותי ודלא
איתיה ברשותי דחמיתיה ודלא חמיתיה.
kol chamira chamira d'iteih birshuti ud'la iteih birshuti d'chamiteih ud'la
chamiteih.
Go on. הפקר. hefker. He doesn't say that though. Nowhere רש"י Rashi
says. He says ליבטל. livatel. He doesn't say הפקר, hefker, right? He
says ליבטל, livatel, and there's significance to this. Now look at... is
it over here?
No, it's in a different תוספות. Tosafot. He says on the משנה...
mishnah... no, was it the משנה? mishnah?
Since הפקר hefker is different than להפקיר? l'hafkir?
Yes, and I'll tell you in a minute.
תוספות Tosafot says,
he says it's an idea of הפקר. hefker. So basically, the point
being that, okay, if it's הפקר, hefker, then it's ownerless. If it's
ownerless, then you know, then it can be around. So what the
ר"ן Ran says though, he... the ר"ן Ran doesn't like this so
much. The ר"ן Ran in the beginning, it's really on the first
דף daf of the ר"ן. Ran. He says that no, you know,
our text of ביטול bitul isn't הפקר hefker because the wording of
ביטול bitul is... is... כעפרא דארעא ke'afra d'ara and it makes no
mention of הפקר, hefker, so it's not הפקר. hefker. And then he
also says there's a big problem. Making הפקר hefker isn't enough. Just
because I make it הפקר hefker doesn't mean it's left my possession.
It may leave my possession once someone else takes it. That's what
he says.
So if it's a form of הפקר, hefker, it's not effective at
all because it wouldn't take into effect until someone takes it, and
no one's allowed to take חמץ on פסח.
In other words, הפקר hefker means legally
it's not only that I've relinquished ownership of it, but someone else,
it's now somebody else's.
Right. Legally, הפקר hefker if I declare my bicycle הפקר, hefker, I
put it out in front of my house and I say anyone
who wants this bicycle can take it.
So if they take it, it's not theft. But until they take
it, it's still my bicycle. Meaning I have a, my bike's in
front of the house, I have a sign, anyone who takes it
can have it. Right. And then somebody walks by and trips over
it and breaks their leg. I can't say it was הפקר, hefker,
I'm not responsible.
According to that, correct.
It's mine and therefore that's like a בור ברשות הרבים, bor birshus
harabim, as you said. Yeah, essentially.
But let me just finish this. So right, no,
perfect logical conclusion to that. So but the point, and also the
biggest problem is ביטול bitul must be done in the heart, right?
הפקר, hefker, דברים שבלב אינן דברים. devarim shebalev einan devarim. So how
does that work? So then what he actually says is he has
a very interesting explanation. So when פסח arrives, right, and I have
my חמץ...
where are you reading from?
This is just from the ר"ן, Ran, but I'm expounding upon it.
In theory, as we mentioned, I should not transgress בל יראה ובל
ימצא bal yera'eh ubal yimatzei because it's not mine, right, that's what
we just got through saying, right?
When פסח comes, I cannot benefit from חמץ, אסור בהנאה, assur bahana'ah,
so therefore I'm not the owner of it. So however,
what we're saying essentially is the Torah puts it back into my
possession to make me עובר over on בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal
yera'eh ubal yimatzei. So consequently, in order to get the חמץ out
of my possession, I don't have to say it's הפקר, hefker, rather
I just need to prevent it from coming back, right? In other
words, if it's הפקר hefker then it wouldn't work. So what I
really need to do is prevent it from coming back into my
possession.
So therefore you don't, you can just do a ביטול bitul even
בלב, balev, because it's not הפקר, hefker, that's the whole point, as
opposed to the other position that says it is הפקר, hefker, the
ר"ן Ran doesn't like that. So basically רש"י Rashi as
explained by the ריטב"א Ritva is saying that also ביטול bitul is
not related to הפקר. hefker. So תוספות Tosafos says it is, but
the ר"ן Ran says it isn't, and רש"י Rashi also sort of
says it isn't, and as he mentioned, he doesn't say הפקר, hefker,
he just says it's like עפר. afar. So basically what's the need
of תשביתו? tashbitu? So I basically, if you will, I'm destroying it
by making it no longer considered a food. It's like עפר, afar,
right? So that's... wait, wait, let me finish. Not literally.
It's in your mind.
In my mind, in my mind. So it's no longer considered a
food. So I'm like, you know, I can physically destroy it, which
would be ביעור, bi'ur, or I can mentally destroy it, right? And
that's what עפרא afra is. So now, you know, our position then,
we say both יבטיל yibatil וליהוי הפקר v'lehevei hefker כעפרא דארעא. ke'afra
d'ara. That's taking both opinions.
We want to be covered either way. If it works for הפקר,
hefker, it'll be הפקר. hefker. If it works by ביטול, bitul, then
it works from that.
So that's kind of what we do. You know, both according to
רש"י Rashi and ר"ן Ran and...
but we still have the problem, I want to understand where we
are at the end of the סוגיא sugya going to the next
משנה, mishna, you still have the problem as to when you can
do that, right?
The fourth, such the fourth hour, the fifth hour.
We haven't addressed that yet. That's still waiting in the wings.
And the interesting part is דעתיה עילויה, da'ateih ilaveih, which is interesting.
I mean, you could have just said that the problem is if
I, you know, if I find this גלוסקא יפה, guluska yafa, right,
then forget about דעתיה עילויה, da'ateih ilaveih, I'm going to eat it.
That's a separate problem, right? You're not allowed to eat חמץ regardless,
but you could say there's a problem that kicks in even beforehand,
דעתיה עילויה, da'ateih ilaveih, and somehow it's not enough to say that
like, you know, it's בל ימצא, bal yimatzei, right, we didn't say
בל ימצא, bal yimatzei, somehow I have to have my דעת da'as
on it in order for it to sort of be back in
my possession. And we're not... you know, then the question would be,
okay, now does that nullify my previous ביטול, bitul, does it not?
But all these other issues.
But we need to stop.
Let's say
I was מבטל, mevatel, I was מבטל mevatel this piece of חמץ
at the right זמן. zman.
I say it'd be a ridiculous question.